i am trying something new instead of me
just winging it i'm going to do
a presentation which will help keep me
on track and also give a little bit of
visual representation so today i want to
talk about
this concept that i can see in the world
it's not quite a dichotomy but i like to
sometimes make things into a dichotomy
in order to um showcase them better so
for every individual that's out there
they are generally either an
overestimator or an underestimator
you want to see the juxtaposition of an
overestimator you would look at trump
someone who thinks they're the best at
everything versus um i like to put
myself in the underestimator category
because there isn't
there isn't necessarily a celebrity one
because we don't put them
in power somebody who is honest about
their traits and
or more so underestimates them and so
this is the presentation
for that it's gonna add this to the
screen
go over here and present it so over and
underestimators and why it matters not
just because it hurts my feelings
so populations are normal not people
which of course isn't quite true the
reason it's called a normal curve is
because it's the normal distribution of
normal people
um it's what normally happens in a
population when you have a continuous
trait
so that is something that cannot be not
like male female where you're generally
either one or the other
it's um a continuous trait right so
weight you could be 120 pounds 120.1.2.3
right it's continuous
height is also continuous and grades
although
we kind of do a b c d e somewhat
uh it's actually zero to one hundred
percent and also falls along continuum
and sometimes they make them fit the
bell curve but generally speaking
anything that is continuous has this
this bell-like curve this normal curve
to it as a population we cannot all
bunch to one side we are going to
have a distribution we are going to have
some of us
fall along along the one tail
and what some of us fall along the other
tail and the vast majority of us are
going to be in the middle
that is why this is big here is this is
the number of people at that trait level
and this is the the trait levels this
would be like extremely short this would
be extremely tall this would be
extremely light this would be extremely
heavy
and this would be the number of people
there i'm hoping you can
see my my cursor on there but i will see
on the replay
so i want to introduce you to blue bob
and red ruby
right here they happen to be overlapped
which is why they look purple
so they are actually identical human
beings nearly they have the exact
same skill level at nearly everything
the difference being
that bob blue bob overestimates himself
and red ruby
underestimates herself so blue bob is an
overestimator and so he slides further
along this which this is going to be a
positive trait this is going to be a
negative trait
she thinks she's worse than she actually
is he thinks he's better they actually
both sit
somewhere in the middle here so
you are in charge of hiring someone you
get red ruby and blue bob's resumes
red ruby describes herself as adequate
at a certain skill level bob says he's
the best at that skill level
again i'm juxtapositioning these are
these are extreme examples of over and
under estimators
ruby thinks she gets along with most
people bob says everybody every single
person he's ever encountered has loved
him
red ruby says you know she rarely gets
sick maybe a couple of sick days
per per year blue bob says he never gets
sick
and so who are you gonna hire i think
hands down nearly everyone is going to
hire blue bob over red ruby
but who's going to actually do a better
job if you hire
both of them and they have the exact
same skill level well no matter how hard
ruby tries she's never going to feel
quite as adequate
so she's gonna keep trying harder and
harder whereas bob feels like he's
he's he's already good he's awesome he's
better than everyone else so why would
he
why would he put in extra effort ruby
he's gonna he's gonna take extra long
breaks because he sees himself as better
than everyone else he's doing more work
so he's entitled to those longer breaks
whereas ruby's going to cut her break
short come in earlier to make up for
that perceived difference that she
doesn't even have
she's going to be extra diligent and
make up for the perceived mistakes
blue bob's gonna leave everything to the
last minute and make mistakes and then
blame them on other people probably
because he won't even see that it's
himself
um he's not going to ever seek outside
advice because there are no
outside advisors that are more competent
than he is
whereas red ruby's going to constantly
be learning and gaining new skills based
on her
underestimation so i just want a few
examples here
they're both cooking dinner for a friend
ruby feels inadequate and so she looks
up how to cook a five
course meal and cooks this beautiful
gourmet meal bob on the other hand is
like i'm the best cook
and just i can follow a recipe mix mac
and cheese
and this is what they present to their
friends again this is assuming they have
the same cookie level
but ruby is an underestimator and bob's
an overestimator
this is they both go to an art class and
do an adequate
average self-portrait but when ruby
looks at hers
she sees this stick figure and when bob
looks at his he sees a work of art
this is they both have the same skill
sets they both have the same information
that is they each have this green this
green slot
so they each know about five percent of
the total knowledge of 100 of what
could be known that all humans know to
all together collectively about this
information
they know five percent but ruby feels
like she only
knows one percent out of this big blue
circle whereas bob
feels like he he knows 25 of it he feels
pretty good
he's pretty confident but they're both
the same
right so why this matters is very much
it comes into the dunning-kruger effect
that most people didn't krieger effect i
feel like i should have looked up an
actual definition because i'm going to
butcher it a little bit because i'm an
underestimator
that when you first encounter something
you go through this
this peak of stupid or you have this
overestimation of confidence that you
know everything and then you realize how
big that circle is that you could know
and you fall into this valley of despair
that you will never know everything
and then you slowly can crawl your way
out in the slope of enlightenment but if
you look at these confidence levels
they're
the same and so if you're hiring someone
you don't know whether they're here in
the plateau of sustainability
after the slope of enlightenment or that
they're here and most people
are here that are over estimators
whereas
because the underestimators fall to this
valley of despair really quickly and
then work really hard to climb out
um they're gonna be more more likely to
gain
the actual competence that is needed now
in this example i tried to make it so
that ruby and bob are the same
so they're going to have the same level
of competence but they're starting at
the same and the point is is being an
underestimator makes you do more work
than being an overestimator so why does
this matter
it matters hugely because of this first
point we hire the overestimators
who will never be confident at doing the
job
we should have hired ruby not bob but
we're always going to hire bob based on
his resume
we judge everyone as overestimators we
that becomes the standard so if somebody
doesn't lie
and and a pad their resume they're never
going to get hired so it forces them to
become an overestimator even when
they're an underestimator
which makes them have even more of this
um imposter complex
same with on a first date right if you
show up and you act like yourself and
you show your flaws
they're going to assume you're not
because that's what how you normally
most people show up on a first date
and so they're going to extrapolate that
if you're this weird on a first date you
must be even way weirder
six months in because they assume
everyone's an understanding or
everyone's gonna show up and
be on their best behavior some of us
don't do that on first dates
we can distinguish between those of the
same level of confidence going back to
the previous slide that we don't know
that that difference
and those who lie outright lie right
just say they have
they're the best at it they're the
overestimators even overestimate their
overestimation
right um or they just have that um
bravado that
that ego that tells them they are better
than everyone else even though
the actual metrics don't don't
show that but this is what our entire
society is based on so we're always
going to put the overestimators in power
either those that believe they're there
like they could take a lie detector and
say they're the best
or those who are lying to say that
they're the best either way
we're putting people who are incompetent
in power because it's the
underestimators who
develop more competence and the
overestimators
who have the confidence it's like the
underestimators stop
the over estimators stop at the point of
confidence in the dunning-kruger effect
here
they stop in the over they stop here the
overestimators whereas the
underestimators continue to go on
and so these are the people who we have
in charge of our business and politics
and these are the people we should have
but these people
generally in this example are the
underestimators and then we're never
going to
even getting to this place you're still
going to talk like an underestimator oh
well there's still more i could know
i just don't know it yet right and so
this is my issue
with how our world works is the very
people who
we should be listening to that is those
with the highest skill set if we are
going to listen to experts
aren't those who are actually in the
positions of power because they're not
the ones who've gotten
the people who are higher than them to
give them the promotions because they're
underestimators
whereas the over estimators every time
there's time for a promotion gets that
that gets the job and so those are the
people in positions of power and it's
costing
all of us endlessly thank you
please like that is hit the little
thumbs up button because it helps the
algorithm
and subscribe if you're not thanks